A type of saturated fat
concentrated in meat and dairy
seems to cause cancer
to metastasize.
Check out the video
to find out more.
"What Causes Cancer to Metastasize
and How to Potentially Help Control it with Diet"
Metastasis formation is the leading
cause of death in cancer patients.
That’s how most people die of cancer.
It’s not the primary tumor, but the
cancer spreading through the body.
“[It’s] estimated that metastasis
is responsible for [90 percent]
of cancer deaths”, with little
progress made in stopping the spread
despite our modern
medical armamentarium.
In fact, we can sometimes make it
worse: Therapy-Induced Metastasis.
All the typical cancer treatments,
radiation, chemotherapy, surgery—
even just poking the tumors
with fine needle biopsies—
have the potential to
contribute to the problem.
I mean, you can imagine
how cutting around a tumor,
severing the blood vessels,
might lead to the
migration of residual tumor cells.
But why chemotherapy?
How might chemo
exacerbate metastases?
Despite reducing the size of
primary tumors, chemotherapy
can change the surrounding tissues,
resulting in an increased
escape of cancer cells
into the blood stream.
Sometimes chemo/surgery/
radiation are entirely justified,
but sometimes these treatments
can make things worse.
If only we had a way to treat the
cause of the cancer spreading.
The development of antimetastatic
therapies has been hampered
by the fact that we haven’t
been able to identity
the cells that initiate metastasis.
But then, this landmark
study was published.
Researchers found a subpopulation
of human cancer cells
“unique in their ability
to initiate metastasis”,
all expressing high levels of
a fat receptor known as CD36,
dubbed “the fat controller.”
It turns out palmitic acid or
a high-fat diet specifically
boosts the metastatic
potential of these cancer cells.
Where do you find palmitic acid?
Although originally
discovered in palm oil,
it’s most concentrated
in meat and dairy.
“Emerging evidence shows
that palmitic acid . . .
serves as a signaling molecule
regulating the progression
and development of many
diseases at the molecular level”,
and that’s the saturated fat
that is recognized by the
CD36 receptor on the cancer cells.
And we know that’s to blame, because
if you block the CD36 receptor,
you block the metastases.
Now this was for a human cancer,
however it was a human cancer
implanted into mice, but clinically
(meaning in cancer patients)
the presence of these CD36-studded
metastasis-initiating cells
does indeed correlate
with a poor prognosis.
For example, CD36 appears to drive
the progression of brain tumors.
If you look at the survival curves,
those with tumors with less
CD36 expression lived
significantly longer.
The same with breast cancer mortality.
No surprise, since “CD36 [appears
to play] a critical role in
[the] proliferation, migration, and…
growth of…breast cancer cells”.
Inhibit CD36, and you can inhibit
“the migration and invasion of
the breast cancer cells.”
Cancer cell migration and invasion
before and after CD36 inhibition.
And not just in “human melanoma-
and breast cancer-derived tumors.”
Now we suspect that “…CD36…drives
ovarian cancer progression
and metastasis” too, since we can
inhibit ovarian cancer cell invasion
and migration and block
both lymph node and
blood-borne metastasis
by blocking CD36.
We see the same kind of
effect with prostate cancer.
Suppress the uptake of fat
by prostate cancer cells,
and you can suppress the tumor.
This was all studied with
receptor-blocking drugs and
antibodies in a laboratory
setting, though.
If these metastasis-initiating
cancer cells particularly rely
on dietary fat to promote the
spread of cancer, why not just
block the dietary fat in the first place?
Cancer cells love fat and cholesterol.
The reason why fat metabolism may
fuel cancer’s spread is because
there is so much energy stored in fat.
“Hence, … metastatic cells might
take advantage of this feature
to obtain the high amount of energy
that is likely to be required
for them to anchor and [set up
shop throughout the body].”
“The time when sugar was considered
as the major, if not only,
fuel to support cancer cell
proliferation is over.”
There appears to be” a
fatter way to metastasize”.
No wonder “…high-fat [diets may] …play
a crucial role in increasing the risk
of different cancer types, …[including]
several advanced cancers.”
Okay, if dietary fat may be “greasing
the wheels of the cancer machine”
might there be speciﬁc dietary
regimens we could use
to starve cancers of dietary fat?
You don’t know until you put it
to the test, which we’ll cover next.
“Metastasis is the leading cause
of cancer-[related death].”
Cancer kills, because cancer spreads.
For example, the five-year
survival rate for women
with localized breast cancer
is nearly 99 percent,
but that drops to just 27 percent
in those with metastasized cancer.
Yet “our ability to eﬀectively
treat metastatic disease
has not changed signiﬁcantly
in the past few decades”.
You know things are getting desperate
when there are papers like this:
“Targeting Metastasis
with Snake Toxins . . .”
Now we do have built-in
defenses, natural killer cells
that roam the body killing
off budding tumors,
and I have videos on boosting
natural killer cell activity.
But as I explained in the last
video, there’s a fat receptor
called CD36 that appears to be
essential for cancer cells to spread,
and these cancer cells respond
to dietary fat intake.
But not all fat.
CD36 is upregulated
by palmitic acid,
as much as a 50-fold
increase within 12 hours.
Palmitic acid is a saturated
fat found in junk food
made from palm oil, but it is
most concentrated in meat and dairy.
This may explain why if you look at
“dietary fat and breast cancer mortality”,
there was no difference in risk
of breast-cancer-speciﬁc death
for women in the highest versus
lowest category of total fat intake,
but you’re about 50 percent more
likely to die of breast cancer
if you eat a lot of saturated fat.
The systematic review and
“…meta-analyses [conclude]… that
saturated fat intake negatively
impacts upon breast cancer survival.”
This may explain why
“intake of high-fat dairy,
but not low-fat dairy,
was related to a higher risk
of mortality after
breast cancer diagnosis.”
If it was the dairy protein,
like casein that was a problem,
the skim milk might be even worse;
but no, it was the saturated
butterfat, maybe because it triggered
that CD36-induced cancer
spreading mechanism.
“…Women who consumed one
or more servings per day
of high-fat dairy had …
[about a 50] percent higher risk
of dying from breast cancer.”
We see the same thing with
“dairy intake in relation
to prostate cancer survival”.
“…Drinking high-fat milk
[appeared to increase] the risk
of dying from prostate cancer
by as much as 600 percent in patients
with localized prostate cancer”,
but “low-fat milk was not associated
with such an increase in risk.”
So, it seemed to be the animal fat,
rather than the animal protein,
and this is consistent with
what Harvard researchers
found in the United States.
More evidence that the fat
receptor CD36 is involved is
“…that the risk of colorectal
cancer for meat consumption
increased from [just doubling
risk to octupling risk]”—
multiplying the odds of
getting cancer eight-fold
for those who carry a
specific type of CD36 gene.
So, “Is It Time to Give
Breast Cancer Patients
a Prescription for a Low-Fat Diet?”
A cancer diagnosis is a “teachable
moment” if there ever was one
to motivate people to make
changes to their lifestyle,
but provision of evidence-based
guidelines is essential
and you don’t know...
until you put it to the test.
“A randomized, prospective,
multicenter clinical trial
to test the effect of a
dietary intervention designed
to reduce fat intake in
women with resected,
early-stage breast cancer…"
(meaning the women had their
breast cancer surgically removed and
were praying it doesn’t come back.)
The dietary intervention group
dropped their fat intake
from about 30 percent of calories
down to 20 percent of calories,
dropped saturated fat
intake about 40 percent
and maintained that 40 percent
lower intake after one year,
three years, five years. And…
“after approximately five years
of follow-up, [the] women in
the dietary intervention group
had a 24 percent lower risk of relapse…”,
a 24-percent lower risk of
the cancer coming back.
That was the WINS study, the Women’s
Intervention Nutrition Study.
Then there was the Women’s Health
Initiative study, where again,
women were randomized to
drop their fat intake down
to about 20 percent of
calories, and again,
those in the dietary intervention
group experienced increased
breast cancer survival, meaning
“a dietary change may be able
to influence breast cancer outcome[s].”
And not only was breast cancer
survival significantly greater;
the women also experienced a
reduction in heart disease
and a reduction in diabetes
as a little side bonus.